Hey everyone! Turn on the subtitles for this
video, so you can see what I'm saying in real time.
It's obvious, right?  It's subtitles, but these
subtitles are more
special because they were generated by this
guy here, which is OpenAI's Whisper, which is
an artificial intelligence model from OpenAI
that will basically do
speech recognition and, through this speech
recognition, it can do
several things; for example, transcribe this
video, which is the subtitle
you're seeing there, or even do the translation.
I'll see later if I do the
translation of this transcription, so that I
have two transcriptions: I have one
subtitle in Portuguese and a subtitle of what
I'm saying, which is more common for us
See; subtitles in a different language, it'll
be a subtitle for English, for example.
We'll talk about that later. So, what we're
going to talk about in this video, just so
you understand, in case you want to, like:
"I want to watch this video or I want to watch the
other one", because I'm going to split this
into two parts. First, Whisper, it
works as a command-line tool. So, I'm going
to focus on the command-line tool, because if we
look here, just by looking at the size
of this thing I wrote here, you'll see the amount
of information we have here just with the
command-line tool. And then, later I'll show you
in the next video how to do the code
implementation using the
Whisper.
Whisper. And you can embed this
into your code and put it, I don't know, in your
Django, wherever you want to work
with Whisper.  You just use the part
from the other video. So, like I said,
we're basically going to focus on the command
line of Whisper here. Another
interesting fact for you: it's because I've
been using Whisper for about six months now,
and I've noticed its strengths and weaknesses,
which I'll tell you about in this video, but
when I went to write this, I got incredibly
curious to know if OpenAI
used this internally. So, the only thing I
thought was to ask ChatGPT
if it could tell me. I asked ChatGPT this: "Does
"Does OpenAI use Whisper internally in any
feature that people consume?". Out of
curiosity, they answered me — I don't know
if it's true, but they said yes — OpenAI
uses Whisper as a basis for audio
transcription and understanding features in
products like ChatGPT with voice input. It's
also used in APIs that
involve speech recognition, like OpenAI's
Speech-to-Text. So, you see
that it's a free, open-source artificial
intelligence model, and it's
used by a huge and very famous company.
That's why I think
it's so good. But what we're going to talk
about in this video is
basically the command-line part of Whisper,
which we'll start now. I'll
Let's use the clip I've been talking about so far,
which for me is about
3 minutes long.  This clip I'm talking about, I'll
cut and use in our
examples.  Alright? So, if you remember what I said
from the beginning of the
video, you can see it in the subtitles, because
I'm not going to replay the
video.  So you can go back to the beginning, see
what I said and see if it's
matching what I'm saying here in the video
transcript. Alright? So let's
get started with this. So, there you go, folks. I've
already done the introduction and I've
put that introduction into another Python script
that automatically cuts the
silence from the video for me. This cut removed
more than 30
seconds of audio. Maybe I was silent for too long
at the beginning of the video
or at the end of the video, something like that.
He already cut this audio, it went to
about 2 minutes and 30 seconds.
So, that's what we're gonna use. I put
the name one-auto.mp4, to say, this is the
first part of the video and it was also
automatically cut for me. Besides that, we
need to understand how we're gonna
run Whisper here. What did I do? I put this
code in a repository that I'll call
`sussu`, `sussu` (rro), in this case. So, our
command there will be `sussu`. And there's
also an official Whisper repository, in case
you want to take a look. I even left a
thing open here too, which was this here,
so you can understand that video
transcription can be used for several
smart and interesting things, too. For example, I use the
video transcriptions to pass this transcription into another API, for
example, Gemini or ChatGPT, GPT-4, or any GPT you want
to use. But I pass this transcription into an AI that generates
summaries of sections for me. So, I send a chunk of the captions, a section of the
captions, into any AI API and give it a
prompt telling it what I want it to do. In this case, it's the video about
argparse that we talked about in Python. It's an hour and a half long. So, I cut it
into seven-minute chunks, pass it to Gemini, and then ask it,
through a prompt, to summarize what I said in that section. And
He goes through it, mentioning
the tools I used, and it's super
helpful. Look, here he's saying
that the main goal of this section is
to introduce a tutorial on how to use
Python's argparse to create command-line
tools. The presenter proposes a practical
challenge: building the CLI interface
for an existing project, allowing external
communication with the program. If you
watch this video, you'll see that's
exactly what I'm talking about in that
video. And then he shows which tools I
used, details the tools, shows the steps
I followed up to this
point, and then gives some tips down
here and so on. And
It does this through snippets, using a for loop, I'm
sending the subtitle pieces to it, and it generates this.  In the end,
you can ask it to do whatever you want. For example, I've already used Gemini
to translate to another language. For instance, Whisper does this, but I
will explain why I used Gemini here. But I've already used it to
translate these subtitles of mine to English or another language, Spanish, and
then it generates several languages from that same transcription for you. I've also
used Gemini to create a general summary of what I said in the video in the form of an
article. It's really good too. And I've also used it to write, and this I
I still use it today to write the video
description and chapters here,
this part here. The final result, content
for YouTube. Chapters for the
video, I asked it for that, and it generates
the chapters.  Okay, then I asked it to
do some SEO optimization for me here, and
it did the video description there. I
forgot to add the title here, but it also
does the title, adds keywords and
so on. So I'm showing you this just so you
can see that
transcribing a video is super powerful
because it gives you the text of what you
said. And from that text you can do
whatever you want with that text there
for your video. Generate a post, translate,
generate a post in another language, in short, whatever
whatever you want. Whatever you can
imagine, you can do with the text
of your video. Alright, that said, the
Whisper here, just so you understand
better, it uses this format here. Why am
I going to show you this? Because
this is super nerdy, but I'm going to
show you this just so you understand
how it works. And I'm also going to give
you tips here, the strengths and
weaknesses of it, I've been using it for
quite a while now, so
I can tell you these things. But
initially what does it do? When you
pass an audio, we talk about audio, but
since Whisper uses FFmpeg, which is
a... We'll get to that, but Whisper uses
FFmpeg. This means that you
You can directly pass a video to it, and
the Whisper code that OpenAI wrote
already converts that video to audio
and that audio into a log-mel spectrogram.
Tough word, but basically, it's this:
Whisper doesn't hear audio, it sees
an image representing that audio, a
graph here, this spectrogram here, which
uses the Mel logarithmic scale, it's a
super nerdy thing here, that for you to
understand you'd have to be an audio
engineer, mathematician, and nerd all at
the same time, so it's kind of complicated.
But Whisper doesn't hear audio, it sees the
image of what you said, and that image is
separated into 30-second chunks. So
it takes your original text, your original
audio, breaks those parts into parts of
30 seconds, run these parts through Whisper,
and it'll do everything it
needs to do there.  There's also the
complete workflow here if you want to see it, because
Whisper doesn't just do audio transcription
and translation, it also does
the following: it can do multilingual speech
recognition, that is, multi-
lingual; it can do that, it can do speech
translation, but
that speech translation is only to English.
So you speak something in
any language, ask it to do translation
instead of transcription; this
translation will go from your language to
English only. If you want to do it in another
language, that's why I used Gemini; if you
want to do it in another language, you
You can also use NLLB, which stands for "No
Languages Left Behind," if I'm not
mistaken, which translates between languages
for 200 languages, in this case. I've already done this
using this, which is the NLLB,
which is this. I already did this
a while ago; if you want, I can bring a
tutorial. It uses Whisper and NLLB to
do exactly that: it transcribes the audio,
in this case, and also translates it
to any language you want. But you can also use, if
you want something more robust, you'll
have to pay a little bit for it, but
you can use Gemini, as was the case with
what I showed you earlier.
Okay, but going back to Whisper, it does
the recognition, the translation, in this case,
it can also identify what language
the audio is spoken in;
this is also cool, if you want to
create a program just to do
language recognition. You can do this,
you can also do — I had thought about
this, but I haven't done it yet —,
but you can also do it, if several
people are speaking in a video and
every hour of the video they're speaking
in different languages, you
could have Whisper do this recognition
and switch the language for it
to start translating into another
language. It doesn't do this automatically; you'd have to
write code for that. And it can also —
this is a part that I
I'm focusing on this part here —, which is
this: it can do what's
called Voice Activity Detection or VAD,
this voice activity detection,
it can, for example, tell where a person
is speaking or where a person is not;
so this would be very useful for me to use
something I use here
that isn't very perfect. I already did this
in the video I recorded for the introduction, which
is basically cutting out silences from the
video; if I'm quiet, I want it to cut
that section. So, if I do this, you
probably didn't see this, because I
was silent for about 5 seconds, but the cut
happened here in this
video, and this was done automatically
here with the auto-editor.  Then I'll
I'll show this too, if you want a tutorial
on it. But using
artificial intelligence, it would be much
more accurate, because what I use
basically uses the sound waves there, it's
not artificial intelligence, but it would
be possible to do this with Whisper, if you
wanted. And one important thing about
Whisper. You can read about it in its
documentation, but I've already written this
here for you. Whisper uses FFmpeg under the
hood, so I left
this text here; I'll leave this whole text
in the video description for you,
so you can read exactly what I'm showing
you here, and then you'll have
all those commands, but it uses FFmpeg, so
you should install it first
so you can continue using Whisper. I've left here the
commands for Debian, Arch Linux, MacOS,
Windows, in several ways
different. You can use these commands here
to install FFmpeg. And
I also created this repository here, the
`sussu` (whisper), that I created here,
which is basically using `uv` to upload
this repository. So the only
thing you need to do is `git clone`, clone
this repository, enter the folder
of what was cloned and run `uv sync`. Of
course, you'll need `uv` to manage the
packages. I've already left a tutorial here
that I've already recorded explaining how to use
`uv`. So, that's it, after you've done
that, another important thing I
I just saw, `uv` will do this for you,
download and install Python 3
.11, this is super important due to
compatibility with Whisper, if you
have a very high version of Python, it won't
install, and it will create your
virtual environment, install the necessary
packages, build both Whisper
and `sussu`. After you do this, `uv sync`,
you'll already have the project
ready, that we can come here and run it for
the first time. So here I
already have that project ready, I'll even
unpin this, and I'll
use it here; I already used `uv sync` here,
I already did this in this project, and then
it already synchronized everything there, and
then now we can run it for the first time. For the
When running it for the first time, we
can run it, or in this case, I'll
exit the terminal just so you can see;
in this case, my editor already activates the
virtual environment automatically. See?
If yours doesn't do that, you can
or manually activate the virtual environment.
I've already talked about this, I won't
focus on that, but you can either activate your
virtual environment manually, or you can
use `uv run` and run Whisper. In this
case, I've already put this here to
Or you can use it like this: `uv run whisper`, or if you activated the
virtual environment, directly with the Whisper command here.
So, Whisper, and then you'll see why
this video might get pretty long,
right? Look at the number of options you
it's here in Whisper. So you have the
audio, the audio that's speaking, it speaks in
`audio file` here, but it can also be video.
I'll show you everything in video here,
but you have this `help`, you have the `model`,
you have all these options here that I
talked about in this article, I even
told you about some that I
think you can use, but you have to
use the running mode, which is the running
mode, which is the running mode, which
is the running mode, which is the running
mode. Look, I've never even used this one
and I don't even know what it's for,
so, I said what it's for, but I said, I
didn't use this. But let's
So, what are the arguments I use most
often in Whisper here? First, the
audio.  As I mentioned, this audio can
also be a video. So, if I
type `whisper`, the path to my file here,
for example, `whisper`, I'll grab
the audio, the first video I recorded here,
which I called `one-auto.mp4`. If I
send this to it, I'm not sending much
information, I'm just telling it
this: look, it's `whisper`, here's the
audio. The audio, actually, that I'm
sending is an MP4 video of the intro.
FFmpeg will handle loading this
audio, it will extract the audio from
the video and then there's code here in
Whisper,
that you can see in the documentation,
that it uses this, because
For example, `load_audio` will load the audio,
for instance, and then it will do this,
this function will use this function here,
and this function will convert this audio into
a 30-second clip.  Then, after that, it will
generate that log-mel spectrogram
it will generate that spectrogram and pass it
into the
`model` here. Then the `model` will detect the
language, it detected the language for it here,
it will decode the options you passed to it here,
and then it will
perform the decoding using the `model`, which is
the model you chose, the graph there,
that graph I showed you, because Whisper doesn't
hear, it sees the audio and the
options, and then it gives you a text result here.
We'll also use
this way, which is much more practical,
basically, you're telling it to
use this specific model here,
do the transcription and get the text. We
will do this in the next video, but
when you run this command I was
showing you, that's basically what it'll
do, it'll do just that, only
it uses the function called `transcribe`
here, so if we
look at the Whisper code itself, in the lib
here, for example, in site-packages, you
will see that it calls this, this
`transcribe` function here. So this function,
oops, this `transcribe` function, let me
see if I can find it here, this function here
`transcribe`, it's basically what I'm
asking it to do there when I pass
like this, and here you have several options,
those options over there, in fact there are
more options there than here, because you
can also pass the decode options
in here, and then it goes in here, and then
it does all this code here, all this,
to do, it will slide through your audio, so
it grabs the first 30
seconds, then slides to the next 30 seconds
and keeps doing that until it finishes the
audio. In fact, in the way we used it, it
uses the previous 30 seconds
to generate the next caption, so it has a
broader context. I'll show you
this here, but you can see that the code is
huge, right? And here's
that CLI you saw, that uses `argparse`,
which we've already talked about on this channel,
Basically, all the options you saw in that help
menu are here,
pure `argparse` right there. So I'm just showing
you what's going on under the hood
here. So, if you hit enter here, it'll use the
`turbo` model. Keep
that in mind, I'll show you the models later, but
if I hit enter
here, what will it do? If it's your first time
doing this, it
will download the `turbo` model first.  It's also
saying here that my
CPU, I'm using a Mac, doesn't support FP16, that
it's
using FP32. That's an option too. It already
detected Portuguese as the
audio I was speaking in that introduction, and
now it's going to
Let's start the translation.  Let's
wait, I'll let it process here.
It's translating and I'll show you the
final result. Look, it's already generating
the subtitles here and I can already
spot a problem; it's generating
huge subtitles, and that would cause a
problem in the end,
because what would happen? I'd have
subtitles that would take up too much space
on screen. We can configure this, but I
want to show you what it
generated. See if you remember if I said
this.  Hey everyone, turn on the subtitles
for this video so you can see in real time
what I'm saying. Obviously, this is
a subtitle, but this subtitle is special
because it was generated by this
Here's the deal, this is OpenAI's Whisper,
an AI model from
OpenAI that basically does speech
recognition, and through that
speech recognition, it can do a lot of
things, for example, transcribe
this video, which is the caption you're
seeing, or even do the
translation. I'll see later if I do the
translation of this transcription. Look how
crazy, I remember well, I think I said
those words precisely. So
it's doing this transcription of the video,
so far I haven't seen any
mistakes. I know where it makes a lot of
mistakes, I'll tell you about it here. But running
the command, just like that, you'll get
a caption like this if it detects it. It's worth
I want to highlight something important here: my
audio is coming from this microphone, which is a
super high-end mic, it's really good. I route
my audio, I'll show you here in OBS, and
it has a noise filter. So this audio you're
hearing is super clean.  It might be that
if your audio isn't as clean, you'll need to
use some of the
options I'm going to show you here. So let's
go, we saw Whisper, just the
process, and then it generated the captions.
Let me also show you where those
captions ended up. So these captions ended up
in the root of my
project here, because I didn't specify where I
wanted it to generate the captions; it
used the same name as the file I sent it,
which was oneauto.json, and
So it generated all the formats it can.  It generated SRT, TSV,
TXT, and VTT. So if you look at the TXT, it's
just the text I said without any
timestamps. If you look at the SRT, for example,
it's the text I spoke in the
exact second I started and finished speaking.
Started speaking and
finished speaking, and so on. And then it has
other formats there, like TSV
as well. I don't know this format, but
apparently it's also from where I started
and where I finished speaking the sentence. It
generated the TXT, which I already showed you, and the
VTT, which looks a lot like SRT, but
basically it's a WebVTT here, which also does
this transcription. It's a subtitle there. Since
I didn't specify, it generated all
These formats here, but we can
provide some information. Now, the
gold standard for me, in my
conception, is JSON, okay? Because JSON,
what's it gonna do? I'm gonna format this
JSON here, so here in the auto-editor, which is Ctrl
Shift I, it formats this text for me.
I'll also hit Alt Z to wrap the
line. And then it gets here, first, the
text, and this is the whole text you
mentioned. This \u is Unicode, it's just a
character that represents an accent, or
some character not in the ASCII table.
But it generates our text there,
nicely, and then it grabs this part
here, this I find super interesting, which
is the segments. The segments, it will have
an ID, which is the sequential ID, so it's like
SRT 0, 1, 2, 3, and so on.  If I'm not
mistaken, SRT starts at 1. But
it will have an ID, a position, when you
started and when you finished
this speech here, pretty; it has the text
of this segment and it has the tokens of this
segment here too. Tokens are important if
you want to suppress
a token; there's that option too. Also the
temperature used, I
will talk about all these things here for
you, but I just want to show you that you
have these options. And these options, as I
told you, are gold here, because these
options give you the possibility of knowing
how the model is detecting your
audio. So we saw where these options came
from. Going back here, what else
What do I have here? I have the following, I'll
look through my text because it's more
organized. I can choose my model here. And
this will now involve
part of your computer, because unfortunately
there's no way for us to run the
Whisper on just any computer. If you don't
have a computer that can run
Whisper, you can use the OpenAI API, which
has an API, if I'm not mistaken,
it uses Whisper and also has versions with
GPT-4, something like that. But you can
check the API, you can use practically the
same things
that I'm going to tell you here. And then I
have the model, the model it uses by default
is the turbo model. The turbo model is
excellent, super fast, but it requires
It requires 6GB of VRAM to run. So, 6GB of
VRAM isn't something just any computer will have.
This here. What is VRAM? Basically, in short,
VRAM is the memory
of your GPU. So basically, you would need a
video card that
has at least 6GB of VRAM to use this turbo
model. Of course, you can
use smaller models, which are faster, but
also less
accurate. So, as I usually use, here I'm on a
Mac M1 Max and this Mac has 32
GB of memory. The Mac has a scheme, check if
your computer has this
too, some computers have this, which is a
scheme that shares the memory
total, which is 32GB, it shares that total
memory with the GPU as well, the Mac
here. So the CPU and GPU use the same
memory block. So whatever I have
available, it will use. This allows me,
for example, to use large models
without any problem, requiring more or
less 10 GB of VRAM, but it runs, it gets
slow, but it runs. So you can use the
tiny, base, small, medium, large, and
turbo models. I'm going over this quickly,
but if you come here, I wrote a lot of
information, a lot of insight here about
things I've been seeing while I've been
using Whisper. So I highly recommend that
you read this and
also watch the video, because I wrote this,
I'm recording the video quickly
for you, to help you out.  And like the
video, comment down below, please!
You guys don't say anything, you don't
engage with this kind of video, so I
have to stop and start making videos
about, I don't know, taking a Nutella bath in the
tub. So it doesn't work. So comment
on the video, say: hi, ok,
everything's fine, just hi, everything's fine,
that's already good, it's already a comment. But getting back here, the tiny
one here requires about 1 GB of VRAM,
so this is already easier to
use. It's not very accurate, but it works
fine. The Base also requires
about 1 GB, okay? So, between the two,
maybe using Base would be better,
because Base, all those that have ".en" at
the end, they work both in English only,
and in English and other languages.  The
others here that don't have ".en" at the end,
They're just multilingual, alright? That's
basically the difference. So, that's why
some have ".en", which means it works
specifically only in English, and
multilingual, but some don't have that here.
So there's Tiny, Base, Small, and
then you'll see the amount of VRAM you need
here. You can test this
as well to see if it runs on your computer.
I usually use this a lot here, when I
have time, because this takes forever, I
usually use the large-v2,
which for me was the best one here, because
I use a lot of technical terms. If I
say any technical term here, for example, I'm
going to say UV sync. If I say
that, if in this subtitle I've already
corrected it, forgive me, but usually
When I say that, it doesn't understand.
When I say "UV add rembg," it won't
understand this phrase I just said.  So, what's
gonna happen is that I'll
have to correct these captions, and that's
where Gemini comes in. I'll give it these captions,
tell it that this was transcribed by... let me
show you here, so you can
understand what I'm talking about. I give this
to Gemini and ask it to
generate... there are several things, there's
a summary, translation, SEO, several things, but
let's use this.  I ask Gemini to correct my
captions with this. So
it's a code here, a script I threw together
quickly, but I pass chunks
of the captions, sections of the captions to it
and tell it, look, you're a
Technical subtitle reviewer in SRT format,
SubRip. The subtitles were
automatically transcribed by an AI,
Whisper, and may contain errors in terms
of programming. I put some code here for
him, these terms here have a lot of
errors, so I say rembg, UV, and so on, I
tell him
to. His job is to correct the words that
are wrong based on the context,
correct the punctuation and add capital
letters at the beginning of sentences, maintain the
original structure of the subtitle to avoid
misaligning the video, respect the blocks,
timestamps and line breaks and so on. I
explain, show an example and
he does all that and he says here, for
example, if I have... this is real,
Okay? If I have a caption that was generated
yes, by Whisper, let me open the
pyproject.toml, did you see what it said there?
To configure Python, this already
happened too, I want you to return to me,
let me open the pyproject.toml
to configure Python. And that's it,
all right? And then I pass this inside the
Gemini, I generate this caption, I generated
this caption, I finish there, putting this
caption on YouTube, making summaries,
making text articles and so on.
So this is super interesting. So I, as I told
you, I usually
use the Large model, but that's up to you
to check on your system
here, in this case. To use the model, you just
have to say "model" and then the model
whatever you want. For example, let's say I
want to use, in this case, the model
Tiny. I've already downloaded all the models here,
because I tested all of this for you,
but then the Tiny model here, it's pretty
fast to do this translation, but it
isn't as accurate as the Turbo. So you see
it already started there, it already
detected the language much faster than... I
don't know if I left that in the
video, but it's much faster than the others.
And if you run it on Tiny and
see that it's not generating that much error,
I'm not seeing much error here, if you see
that it's not generating that much error, you
can use Tiny, because it's way faster
and consumes much less of your computer's
resources. Now let me show you
This is the same code I ran with the
Large model, just so you can see the difference. It
will take forever to show you the
first one. So Large-v2, which is what
I like to use when I have
time, keep an eye on it and I'll be
opening my system right now, just
so you can see how many resources it's
consuming from my system. Let me
reduce the screen size for you to see.
Now that it's starting, see? I'm
talking to you here
so I don't cut this video.
Look, it's consuming about 6 GB
or so from my computer, but
I've already noticed that these 6 GB it's
consuming from my computer, it will
increase as the video gets longer
it's longer. So it'll reach those
10 MB or so at some point in the
video. See, it hasn't even started
processing the first language yet. So I'm not
gonna let it do that, I just wanted you
to see how many resources this
model uses on your computer.
Hit Ctrl+C to stop it. If I go back to
the Tiny one, let's see how much it uses
here. Back to Tiny, look, the
Python here is using 388 MB and it's
already doing the whole job there. That's
as I told you, because my video is 3
minutes long, if I'm not mistaken, so
it's a shorter video, but it can keep going
up until it reaches 1 GB of memory, depending on the
model you use. So that's it about the model.
Let me close this and the
You can check out other options here.
Going back, I have the device. That's
here, if you have an Nvidia card
with CUDA drivers and a compatible version
with PyTorch, you can also use the
CUDA device. In my case, I don't
have a video card, because as I told
you, I'm on a Mac, so I just
had to use this. I'll keep Tiny here
for now, but I'll put the
device here and, in my case, this is
already the default, so I don't need to add it, but
in my case I put device CPU here and then
you would put CUDA if you had the
Nvidia card. The output_dir is important
to avoid overloading my code too much, which
it dumped everything here, so I'm going to put
everything here, I'm going to delete all this and I'm going to
always save it to the "transcriptions" folder,
for example, so "-o" or "--output_dir",
let me see, that's right, "-o" or
"--output_dir", and you can also choose the
format, which defaults to "all", it already
includes all the formats it can handle. So I
will put a "-o", and I'll put
"transcriptions" here, and it will create
the folder if it doesn't exist. Let me
cancel this and do the
following. Another option there, that you see
whenever it gives a warning at the
beginning, saying this, two warnings:
first, this computer, which is a
Mac, doesn't support this FP16, so it will
use FP32, which is float 32,
float 32. FP16 is usually faster,
so that's why it tries first
it uses FP16; if it doesn't support it, it switches
to 32, which is the case on this computer
here. And also this one here, it's saying: "Look,
I'm detecting the language,
but if you want, use "--language", to
specify the correct language so
you don't get this warning.
So basically here, I'll say the
following: --device CPU, transcriptions and
then --FP16 false, on my computer,
in this case here, just so it doesn't give
that warning, "--language", here I'll
put PT, for PT-BR. "Language" is the language
spoken in the video. So, if we look
here, I want all formats.
So, if you want, just put "-f",
any of these formats you want to use here.
And here I left an example
for you. Another thing is: it does two things, it does this, and this I'm
talking about here is the Whisper code. The
model does more than that, it does
those things that are in the model, okay?
So we're talking about two separate things
here. I'm talking about the code we're
using, the command we're using.
This command line, it receives two options:
either transcribe or
translate. Both do transcription; the only
difference is that transcribe
transcribes to the language spoken in the
video, and translate will do that, but it
will only generate English. So it will see
what you're saying in the video and
will translate that to English. As I told
you, you can use the transcription
the video's language to translate using
any Gemini or GPT API.  So here, or any
other, I'm just
guessing the ones I've already used, but
there are others. So here we can put the
task there, so --task, this is already
standard, I'm putting this here just so you
know. So transcribe here, or translate,
this is the standard transcribe.
Another thing we can use, which we already
saw there, is the `language`, right?
The `language`, what language is spoken in
the video? Sometimes you are, for example,
a while ago I did one of an anime here,
okay? And then I needed to use the
language spoken in the video, I don't even
remember, I don't know if it was Japanese,
Korean, I don't know what
which is, but I had to use a language
from here, but it's hard to know what it is,
I don't know what these letters are. So
you can take the long form here of the
`name`, okay? So you can take, for
example, here, there's a proper name, in
at some point you'll see, Portuguese.
You can use both ways, both with the
short form, which is this, which I'm
using there, or the long form, `language`
Portuguese. Okay. If you want to see, you
can go to the Whisper code, `tokenizer`
`languages`, and then you'll see its
`languages`, just go to the Python `lib`, there
where you're downloading your packages in
your virtual environment, and in the `tokenizer`
you have `languages` here, which is this.
And then you have the short and long forms
it's long there, which is the format it uses
there. So, they're all here, you can
check them out here too.  Alright, having said that,
we've already seen this, this,
`--temperature`, okay? So let's look at these
parts here, because these parts start to
get into more obscure areas, because here you'll be messing with the `model`, you
will specify how you want it to
work, okay? But let's do this,
let's just run this command
here, I'll wait for it to finish, I won't
make you wait, obviously, but let's
run this command, just so it gets
saved there, and then we'll continue talking
about the temperature part, `--beam_size`,
these things that are also interesting.
So folks, the model's temperature
Here. When you talk about temperature, in
any AI model
you're going to use, at least most of
the ones I've used have
temperature. You're basically talking
about the model's creativity.  Like, you
will give it more freedom to be more
creative, try more options, or you'll
tell it to be strict and try only that
specific option. This
connects to other parts here, in these
lower parts, which I'll
explain nicely. But always think about
this, the model's creativity. The lower
the number, the number here in Whisper
goes from 0 to 1, and you can use a
`float` as well, so 0.something, up to 1.
In this case, in Whisper, 0 is like 0
creativity, that's my go-to. I try, because of how my
audio is recorded here, for example, the
microphone is very clean, I don't use much
slang, I use a lot of technical terms, okay?
But even with temperature 0 or
temperature 1, in my case, it doesn't change much,
it will try another word, in a
different way there, but it doesn't change much.
So I always leave the temperature as
0, but that will depend, as I'm telling you, on the
quality of your audio, on the
thing the person is saying within
that audio, which model you're
using, is it Tiny, is it Large, is it
Turbo, so it depends on several factors
here. It's up to you to test and see what
comes out for you. As I'm telling you,
Most of the time, I use temperature 0.  But temperature 0 activates
certain options, and if you start increasing the temperature, giving more
freedom to the model to choose certain things, you can also use
other options. It's almost like an IF statement; I even created a
table below for you to understand this. But let's say I have
temperature 0. Temperature 0 means 0 creativity, but I can still
configure --beam_size and --patience.  Basically, --beam_size will be the number
of hypotheses you keep in parallel. So the model will do the following:
you said a certain word, and the model isn't so sure about a certain
Given a word, it will give several possibilities
for it to choose from. And then, based
on those possibilities, it will choose the one
that has the highest probability of being what
you said in the video. So this is basically
giving more hypotheses to the
model, so it can select one. And patience is
the patience it has
to choose the words. So patience is the
tolerance factor that makes
the model continue exploring new hypotheses
after finding an acceptable one.
So this and this, both --beam size and
--patience, are basically
used only with temperature 0. If the
temperature is greater than 0, in this case
you need to use --best_of here. And another
thing is,
--patience here basically multiplies the
--beam_size. So if I have, I'm
speaking as a layman here.  The
--beam_size is 2, for example. If you set
--temperature to 0, --beam_size to 2 and --patience to 2,
I'm basically multiplying the --beam_size.
So it's like I'm telling it, choose
--beam_size 2, two hypotheses
of what you said, and do that twice.
--patience. That's basically what
I understood about this, in this case. But
another thing you can do
is greedy mode. Greedy mode means it finds
only one hypothesis and uses that hypothesis,
which makes the code a little faster.
Not a little, much faster. Because
the more hypotheses you give the model
and the more patience, the slower it will be
to choose a specific option. So if
I want, for example, --temperature 0 and
--beam_size 1, this, patience doesn't
work here. The --patience won't
work. If I set --temperature 0 and
--beam_size greater than 1, then patience
kicks in.  Understand the logic? So
that's basically it. This with
--temperature 0. If I have --temperature
greater than 0, that is, more
creativity, then it works differently.
Here with --beam_size it
uses hypotheses. In --best_of, it will
choose samples. It will take several
different samples of what it has and then
it will choose among the specific
samples there. You can test both options.
As I told you, I tested
All of this before mentioning this
to you, and in my case, I didn't see much
difference. I researched all about
this, and what happens is that this will
kick in when you have very bad audio or
when the person is speaking
a lot of slang or a lot of technical terms in
that particular video, then this will kick in
here. And a quick tip here for you is: when
the temperature
is greater than 0, it will use samples,
sampling. So here in this
case, only the --best_of option works, and
the default is 5 samples that it uses.
When you set the temperature above 0, it
automatically does this, but if
you want to change it for more or less
samples, you can use this option.
When the temperature is 0, it uses Beam
Search, and in this case, which are
the hypotheses, it will by default use 5
Beam Search, 5 hypotheses, and the
default --patience is 1. So these will
only be 5 hypotheses. If I increase
the --patience here, as I told you before,
I'm basically going to multiply my
number of hypotheses. Again, that's what I
understood from this. What does it do?
Because I was also looking at the code,
how the code was written, so I
went deep into this. And here in this case
this part is ignored, the Best
Of is ignored. Whenever the temperature is
0, the --best_of is ignored. The temperature
equal to 0 and --beam_size equal to 1, this
is called greedy. It will basically find
Let's try the first option and use it, don't
overthink it, it's usually faster.
It's pretty quick here. The default is temperature 0 and
--beam_size equals 5, alright? That's the
default. If we change that, we can even see if it'll be faster. So
if I set, for example, temperature 0 and
--beam_size equals 1, which will be the
greedy, the Tiny model should be much faster
here than the way I was using it
before. You see it's already spitting out
almost the entire caption,
it'll reach the end in, I don't know, 10
seconds. That's because I used the Tiny
model, but there's also a higher chance of it
making mistakes. A quick tip for you:
When you use the default options, the way
Whisper comes, it already works, for
For me, at least, it works perfectly.
You don't need to change much about how
the model works. I explain everything here
for you, I even show you in practice, the
model will respond the way it was trained,
regardless of your tweaking in the
configs. So, changing the temperature, beam
size, --patience and so on, maybe, depending
on your audio, might be a waste of time.
When would I change this,
if I were to change it?  Many times, this
also depends on the audio, this has happened
to me a few times, the model might get
stuck in a loop. Like, it picks up a
word, the last word it detected there, like
"1", it says "1", then it keeps
saying "1", "1", "1", until those 30
seconds are up. So, it gets stuck in a loop.
In that case, then I start tweaking the
--beam_size, --patience, and so on, and
there are other options down there that can
also change how the model works
there. Another thing that's already there, by
default, is --temperature Increment on
Fallback. If it discards a certain option, it
will try again,
basically, with this option here. By
default, this option raises the
temperature to 0.2, and then, anyway, it will
try to generate some text
there for you. If it can detect anything, it
will generate some text
there for you, or if it can't, it will loop,
then you start to
use the options. This is super interesting,
which is the following: Max Line
Width is basically the line width.
So, here, you're noticing that it's
generating huge captions.  This doesn't
always happen, it's good to test this,
because what happens? Sometimes, it
generates captions
in the perfect size for you. But if you
let the model generate the captions,
what can happen is exactly this. Because,
for me, these captions it's
generating here, let me see how many
characters are in this line, it's
generating 102 characters in one line,
it's hard to read. So, I usually generate
the caption with a width of 42, more or
less, or you can also choose the words.
But let's look at the options here. By
default, in the hardcoded code it's 1000
size, that's why it allows the model to
generate this. It's in the Subtitles
Writer, in their class. But here, I told
you 42, I put 45 here, I
use 42, I did. Later, if I remember, I'll
correct this. But this will
correct it, but this requires you to
enable --words_timestamp. Because what
happens? Then it will start tagging by
word. So, it starts tagging the
timestamp of where you spoke and
finished. In this case, it tags by
word specifically. So, each word has its
start, end, start,
end, start and end. This allows you to
make almost a karaoke there. Because what
will happen? You can enable an option
that is --highlight_words, I don't know if
I added this option here, but it underlines
everything you're saying,
the exact moment you're saying it.  Only
thing is, this takes a little longer.
But let's test it. What do we need to do?
First, I need to set
`words_timestamps` to `True`. Let's add it
here to the command. I'll add `words_`
`timestamps` as `True`. I'll add this
option `--max_line_width`, alright. And then I'll
add another option here to explain to you.
This `--max_line_width` I'll set to
42, as I told you, and the `--max_line_count` I
want it to generate a maximum of two
lines. This `max` is confusing, because in my
opinion it's not maximum, it's `line_`
`count`. Why does this happen? When you
enable this option, what will happen is
so now my captions will always
have two lines. And that doesn't come from the `model`
here, you'll see that, if I'm not
mistaken, when it generates, here when it
generates, that's not where it works.  That's
in the final caption. So here it keeps
generating the same way, but in the final
caption, look how it turned out. It generates
up to 42 characters, it gave 41 on this line and
two lines. But notice something, because
what was I saying about `max` potentially
misleading us?  `max` isn't `max`,
it's literally two lines. Because look, all
the captions now have two
lines. Two lines, two lines and so on and so
forth. So that's what
this does. Instead of using `line_width` here, you can
also use
You can also use the number of `words` per
line, `--max_words_per_line`. This option
lets you specify how many words you want per
line, but this
option is overridden if you use `--max_line_width`.
You use either `--max_words_per_line`
or `--max_line_width`. I don't use this
option; I use the top two
I mentioned. And this `--highlight_words`
is super interesting because what
happens? Let me show you; it's really cool.
All these options I'm
talking about require `words_timestamps`,
and this tends to make the
command a little slower.  Not just a little,
sometimes depending on the
module it makes your command much slower.
I'll generate this and I'll show you
Let me show you this `--highlight_words`
`True`, in this case. I don't know if I added this
option here. `--highlight_words` is this.
This `--highlight_words` that I put here,
I didn't set the value, later if I remember
I'll change it. The value here is to
enable it, so you have to put `True`
in front, as I put
here. So let me run this to see what it says.
So it's generating the normal subtitles and I
want to show you that it will tell me this
here at the time I'm saying the words.
So look how cool, let
me see if I can enable this for you to see.
I'll grab our video, the
video here, let me prepare everything here and
I'll show you. I'm putting the video
Here, in the video I'm running, I'll go to
the subtitles, I'll add a subtitle and I'll
go where I'm recording the transcription
and I'll put this here,
this subtitle we generated. So notice
with me, let me try
to make this better for you to understand.
Let me add a background.
Notice with me that it's underlining each
word I'm
speaking, precisely when I say the word.
Look, this is super cool.
Let me just listen here to see if it's
working. Perfect, it's hitting
perfectly here the word with where it's
underlining, so it makes almost a
karaoke effect, but it's a little slower,
unfortunately. So okay,
we generated this subtitle with all these
options here. So here I put a
the full command for you to see, I
added this backslash here just to
break the line, but you usually write
all of this on a single line
in Unix, Linux, or Mac, I write the
command like this, but these
backslashes are just showing that I
broke the line here to show you this
full command. Oh, another interesting
thing we have here in Whisper is the
`--initial_prompt`, which is as follows, okay? This
gave me a hard time, because I tested
it in several ways and ended up not
seeing much use, I didn't see much
function in this. Why? What happens?
This serves, honestly, to
confuse the module, in my opinion,
because what is this
Option? It's the first context of the first
30 seconds of the video. So what does it do?
Whisper converts the first 30 seconds and
from the second it takes the
context of the previous one, in this case.
So the first 30 seconds it's kind of
contextless. If you want to use this
`--initial_prompt`, you can give it a hint
to it, say look, in this I said a certain
thing. I've already tried using this
here in every way you can imagine, saying
which words I'm
talking about throughout the whole video,
talking about what the video is about, there are some
discussions here in the OpenAI repository
that talk about this. I tested with
some options here, I didn't see much
interesting functionality in this,
at least in the command line.  Later in the
code, this might behave differently.
here. But as I'm telling you, this works
really well in the first 30 seconds.
If in the first 30 seconds you say a word
that it misinterprets,
you can use the `--initial_prompt` flag
and specify what you're saying. For example,
in the test I ran, I was talking about
REMBG, which removes the background from
images. In that case, I took a short clip,
cut a snippet from the video, and
said where I mentioned REMBG. So, in that
case, if I specify in the `--initial_prompt`
that I said the word REMBG, because it
misinterprets this word, if I
tell it that, it understands and corrects it
within the first 30 seconds. If in the second,
within those first 30 seconds, in the next
block, I don't say the word REMBG,
because in the first one I said REMBG,
it got it right. In the second one, if I say REMBG,
it will pick up the context from the
previous 30 seconds and not this --initial_prompt.
So what will happen is that, since I said
the same word twice in both blocks
it gets it right again. If in the third
block I don't say REMBG and then in the
fourth one I do, it lost that context,
then it will start to get it wrong again. So
I thought this could be very useful if
you want to give the name, someone
said your name at the beginning of the
sentence, it got it wrong, something like that, only in the
first 30 seconds. And then it depends on
the repetition, in this case, as I was telling you
explaining. So, --initial_prompt, I won't
even use it, but basically you would give
it a little nudge. I even left an analogy
here for you to understand better.
Imagine you're backstage and you're going
to give a hint to a
singer. The singer is about to go on stage,
you say: "Hey, there are 300,000
people waiting for you". The singer will go
on stage, see those 300,000
people, the first 30 seconds, and then it's
the show, and then they forget, they've
forgotten about it. So they'll keep doing
their show, but the context you gave
was just for them to take that first step
on stage, the rest is up to them. So, that's
why you use this. This can also cause some
problems,
as I told you. Depending on how you write
that --initial_prompt, you
can make the model start generating huge
captions, you can make the model
get into a repetition loop. So, that's why
I said honestly that this
is kind of to confuse the model and
whoever will use the model, because if you
use this wrong, your transcription will be
weird.  That said, you can also
do the following: if you want to test the
--initial_prompt, you can cut the video
with FFmpeg. So FFmpeg, as you had to
install it to use Whisper,
FFmpeg receives a command like this: `ffmpeg`
and `"-i"`, the input, and to be faster
you copy the video codec, `-c:v`, `copy`,
copy the audio codec `-c:a`,
`copy`, and then you can specify where you
want that video to start, the cut
point. In this case, it's five minutes,
so it will start the video from the five
minute mark, and where I want it to end, `-to`
in this case, which will end at 10
minutes. What am I going to do? Imagine that
my video is 30 minutes long, I'm going to take
from, I'm going to generate a new video that
starts at the five-minute mark of this video,
going up to 10 minutes. In other words, I'm
going to generate a five-minute clip of this video
using FFmpeg. And then I have a new video.
That's one way to test it. Another way to
test is using the `clip` `timestamps` option
in Whisper itself, where you
specify the starting and ending seconds, where
you want it to start
transcription. And in this case, it will
leave, it will only grab the video at the
location you mentioned, and then it will do the
transcription. I'll explain better later
on. This --clip_timestamps. Here I've
already explained the FFmpeg command. Here
it's also the following, this is what I
was telling you, this comes by default, but
you can disable it. When the model uses the
first 30 seconds, from here on it
will always, by default, use the
context of the previous 30 seconds, in the
next context. So, from the second onwards it
always has the previous 30 seconds
as context. This makes the model basically
have a minute of
video context, so it doesn't get lost,
it knows what you were saying before,
so it doesn't always start from scratch.
Because we know that the more
context we have, the better. So, it does
this by default, grabbing the context from the
previous block. But if you see that this is
generating an error loop, that
problem, is generating some error that's
making it carry that error to other
blocks, you can test, disable it. Just set
`condition_on_previous_text`
to false. And then, in that case, it will be
conditioned to not use any context,
it will only use the 30 seconds of audio,
which may also make your text less
consistent, right? In this case, because it
won't remember what it said in the previous 30
seconds, but there's this option here. Okay,
I left some recommendations
Here's one for you, and here are some parameters
I didn't use, or barely used, but that
are interesting for you to see. I didn't
test `length_penalty` here. It controls the
penalization of long sequences, typical value
between 0.6 and 1. I didn't test it, just
looked up what it does, so I won't even go
into details about it here.
This one is interesting, I've used this one
a few times. This one, `suppress_`
tokens, it allows you to cut out some things
that might be garbage for the
model. Sometimes you'll say, it already does
this by default, it already comes with `-1` which
will cut most things. Oh, hum, those little
things we say,
noises that it might detect as noise or speech,
it already cuts those things
automatically with `-1`. But if you want to
be specific, you can grab the
tokens here and pass them to this `suppress_`
tokens here. Here's an example for you.
This will cut out some useful things.
Just as an example for you, if your text
is "Hi everyone, this is my text, with a
comma". Imagine this, "Hi everyone,
comma, this is my text, period". If I pass
these tokens here, which are these
ones I put down here, from this whole
sentence, your text won't have any
of these things. So, your text will be
without commas, without "Hi", without
"everyone", and without a period. Look, I'm
gonna grab this and show you this
how it works. I'll come here, you see
there are several commas here and there must be
Let me see if I can find a period somewhere.
Apparently, it
didn't generate any periods here, but the
commas. With those `suppress_tokens`, I
am suppressing a comma there too, which I
copied from there. So, if I run
this command, it won't put any commas
here in the text. So, I'll run it
just so you can see. Look, it's not putting
any commas and it already changed the
behavior. You're seeing that it already
changed how it generates the caption width
for some reason. You have to keep testing
to see what will happen. Each thing
I do here changes how it works. Now it's
generating captions
that are usable, they are much shorter, but
I was already passing the `--max_line_count` option
There it is. And here's the underline I
showed you before, but I was already
passing the `--max_line_count` options,
so it changed here. But it looks weird,
you see, it should have a period
or a comma to go from here to there and
so on. So, it's worth testing this
information. It's super interesting,
but as I told you, test them first.
If you want to know what the tokens are
here, I just went into Python, just to
show you. I went into regular Python
here, and if I do a `print(1, 2, 3)`,
you've probably seen this before, obviously, right?
But I'm just in regular Python, so what
can I do? I'm already in this project
here with the virtual environment active. So,
if I import `from whisper.tokenizer`
`import get_tokenizer`, it will import. Okay,
imported. If I say `tokenizer =`
`get_tokenizer(True)`, the first
argument is `multilingual`, it's `multilingual`, I
want it. The number of languages Whisper
supports, 99 in this case, I think it's 99,
I know. The Portuguese language I'll be
using and the `task` which is `transcribe`, I
can use this `tokenizer`. So now I can say,
for example, here in the option
there, I was getting there, folks, comma,
this is my text. If you want to convert
a text into tokens, you use `encode`, for
example, `token.encode` and then you can say
there, "Hello world", these are the tokens the
model picks up there. In this case, `token`
`.encode`, what did I put? `tokenizer`,
people, I put `token`. `tokenizer`
`.encode` shows which tokens I got.  Ah, I want to know
what's 401. `tokenizer.decode`, and then I pass a list
with the tokens I
want. I only want 401, which is? It's "Hi", in this case,
see? "Hi". And the next one
is 842, it will be "A", a regular "A". The other one
is 7968, which is "world". So, if I pass
all these tokens here, it should generate, it shouldn't
generate, right? It will generate what I
told you, which is the text there. So here, "Hi world",
was the word that this
`tokenizer` generated. So this is interesting for you to
know which token and
also, besides this, okay? What I'm saying is for you to
know which
token, in case you want, look, I want to
see which token it's generating here.
But another thing you can do
is this, go to the JSON that
it generates and then you can take a look. I think
it's harder and less precise this way, but
you can do it like this. If I take here
any text that it spoke there, I
can see which tokens it generated
here. So this should match here.
This should be a space, right? This
initial one here. Let's look here, this
one, 50364. I think that's a space
over there. Let's see. Yeah, it really is an
empty text, you see? But just so you
understand what I was telling you,
you can look here at what it
generated, okay? And it doesn't match exactly, as you
see that the word "hello", it took "OL" and "A"
separately, it doesn't match exactly here. So I
I think there's a more precise way I showed you,
so I know what each thing is.
For example, if I take this here, this list,
and put it there, we can see, decode this list.
So, pasting it here will be wrong because of
the following. Let me fix it here, to avoid any
indentation. And then we look at that.  So
looking at it now, see? It looks
super weird. I pasted it, now it's going. So,
look, "hello", then we'll see what I'm
talking about, okay? So it's basically this.
And then, it seems the Tiny model is
super imprecise here, okay? So I like to use
larger models, but I'm
using Tiny here just to show you faster what
it's doing.
I'm using Tiny here just to show you quickly
what it's doing.
generating. So let's look at other options.
This FP16 is float16 or float32. Float16
tends to be faster, right? It's faster.
So, here, to prevent it from generating
a warning, I think I already set it,
didn't I? Let me see. Yes, I did, see?
To prevent it from generating a warning,
I set FP16 to false. But don't do that,
if it doesn't generate a warning, it's
using FP16 there. And this is one of
the first lines of code from the
`transcribe`. If you look in `transcribe`,
which is this function here, it's one of
the first lines there that I was showing
you before. What is it checking here?
Let me see up here. Here, at the
beginning, it will check if your
`device`, in this case, if you are
saying you want FP16 as a `tool`, or
if you don't specify, it will
try 32. But I think that's it here.
It will check if the model `device` is
a CPU, then it won't use FP32.  Yeah,
that's it. Then it checks if the
device has CUDA, in this case, if it
goes in here, because if you're
using a CPU and so on. I'm reading the
code here, more or less,
for you, but it's from the first few
lines here, where it tells you, look, if your
device doesn't support FP16, it will
use FP32. For the next options,
let's look here. This is interesting
too, which is the following, `Compression`
`Ratio Threshold`. This does the
following, it will, imagine you have
Here's a word, a phrase of that type,
it keeps repeating the same thing here.
When you compress this with Gzip,
which is what it uses here, what will
happen is that the compression ratio gets
very high, because if you repeat a lot of
things, the compression is smart enough
to throw all those things
into one thing. And then the compression
is high, you compressed that section a lot.
When you say something much more
diverse, with several separate words,
which is how we usually speak, the
compression is lower. So what
happens? It can detect if, in a certain
section, Whisper got into a
loop, repeating a certain thing there. If
that happens to you, you can
let's try setting the Compression Ratio to zero, and then
let's see if that improves things or
not. The default value is 2.4. I don't remember
if that's in that JSON file, let me see
here. That JSON file generated for us,
it has it. Look, here's my Compression
Ratio, from that section I was looking at,
which is this little section here, this
one up here, this Compression Ratio was
one point, that's the whole value here. That's why
I was telling you that this JSON is
super important for us, because it
shows how the model is performing.
So in this case, it's within the
standard. If it went over 2.4, we'd
have a problem. This isn't something
I change much unless I have a problem, I always keep the default. But
as I'm telling you, the compression ratio is
exactly what you see in the JSON.  You can
check it if your model gets stuck in a loop,
or if it's generating
something really messed up, you can also
check the compression ratio there
in the JSON and see if it's exceeding the
standard, which is 2.4. I don't think any of
mine goes above 2.4. Let me look it up and
check. They're all around 1.7
something, all of them. This one went up a
little, 1.89. It stays in that range. None
went above 2.0 here, the compression ratio.
Because we usually talk about
very diverse words here, so we usually won't
have a problem with that. But
this one got pretty high, it got to 1.9. It
was higher than I've seen so far, but if you
No problem, you can test this option here too. Let's look here
below, this log probe threshold also has
the AVG, if you see, it's this, AVG
log probe. And then it gives you a value here
of this log probe. Let me go back there to
see. This is the average of the
log probability. Complex stuff,
right? If the average of the log
probability, log probe, of the tokens
is below the value, in this case, it
treats it as an error. I messed up. Then it
goes to the fallback, uses a higher
temperature. But the default is minus 1. So
you can see the AVG log probe, the average
of the log probability of the sentences
transcribed by Whisper using that JSON
I showed you at the end. I already told you
from this JSON, right? See here? This is
the average, the default value is -1. So
If it falls below this value, it'll
consider that an error and then
it will try again with a higher
temperature, which is that fallback
temperature there. Again, I'll repeat
this for you, because I only used these
options to make this video, to talk about
Whisper. It's not something I
use all the time. I've said this a few
times already. So if I'm
wrong, I researched it, asked the AI,
I read the paper here from OpenAI, this
paper here, you can read it too, it's more
like, it explains how the model was trained, but
I read their whole paper to explain these
things to you. So it's not a
It's something I'm figuring out,
but I'm not 100% sure either.
about what's going on. I don't think
even the model team is 100% sure
how the model works, because many times
you see the researchers talking and it seems
like they're saying the model behaved
this way, as if the model
had a life of its own. But you can
test these options, take a look
here, because this was the basis of a lot
of research and, as I told you, read the paper,
read everything. This is the no
speech threshold, I don't remember having
used this, but this is something that
interests me, which is the following: the model
can detect periods of silence. If the
model thinks it's silence, it will
Using this token here, in the speech,
speaking and the decoding fails. It
discards this section as silence,
this helps cut breaths, these
things, or even some strange noise there,
that appears, noise won't be silence,
so it discards what I said. But this
here it will treat as silence and this is
a part that interests me, which is
that VAD there, that I was looking at
maybe trying to do something that cuts
the silences of the videos using AI,
but that's something for the future,
let me know if you want me to talk about this
here later. This part here,
gave me a headache, but wow
man, I tested this a lot,
because what happens? I'll explain the
That's my problem here. I mostly, 90% of the time, worked with
my native language, Portuguese.  At times I worked with
Japanese, Korean, English, if I'm not mistaken.  I worked with a few languages, but that
was a specific, separate case. But what happens? None of the languages I
tested have punctuation coming after the words, because there are languages where the
punctuation starts at the beginning of the word. This "prepend punctuation," as I understand it,
means this argument controls which punctuation characters
appear before a word and should be attached to the following word instead of
being treated as a separate token. What does this mean? Here, if I took
Here's a segment, you see
what it does? Look, if we
observe, it does the following: in the text
it's this, this text is this segment,
alright? Imagine there's punctuation here
at the beginning, I don't know, I think in Spanish
it might be like "está", in this case.  At that
beginning punctuation, it has two options,
the model can either separate that punctuation
into a separate word here, or it can
join that punctuation with the following word,
which would basically be, imagine
that there's punctuation behind it, imagine here,
it can treat the upside-down question mark
as a standalone mark, or it can attach it
to that word, that's what that does.
So, when you say this option here,
you're basically saying, this is the default,
So he says to include quotes, parentheses,
commas, requires `words_timestamps=true` as well,
which is, you know, to create timestamps per
word. And then I said, in theory, if the
model generated, for example, this snippet,
this I think is real, I think
that word "argument", it's split into
three pieces, but if it generated "argument",
here, separately, like this, these
tokens here, let's look at these two tokens
just to confirm, I don't know if
I left that open, I think I didn't
leave that open, no, it doesn't even, but,
this would be the representation of this
here, in this case. Notice that there's a
punctuation mark here, this punctuation,
it's separated from this "arg" here, if I
do this and don't put this
Regarding punctuation here, what it will do is
handle both this and this
separately. If I use the pattern this way,
it will join this with this
word here. I left an important note for you:
I tested Whisper
mostly with two languages, Portuguese and
English. I tested one or
another, but very little. And what happens
here, in my use case, is that I didn't
see any place where it generated previous
punctuation. I even looked at
the Whisper code functions, which are the
functions that do this,
which is in the `timing`, if I'm not mistaken,
which is here, let me see if it's this
one, it's this one, it's this function here,
which is in the `timing`, which is this
`merge_punctuations` here, it receives
these things, it receives a list of
words, basically, it has word tokens
here, but it receives a list
with the words separated, and then it
receives what you're going to do the `prepend`,
from that
option, and the `append`, which I haven't
mentioned yet, but it's there later, I managed to see that.  And then
what it does is go in here, see if the
word has, this I found strange, it
checks if the previous word starts with a
space, and I noticed that the punctuation in
Whisper doesn't have a space, so I found
that strange, but okay. So
it checks if the previous word starts with
a space, and if the previous word without the
space, which is the punctuation without a space,
is in what you're passing here, and then it does
This whole operation is about joining or separating
punctuation marks. This is for `prepend`,
I couldn't see prepend, but append,
which is the "after" part, I could see that,
and append, let me go back here, append,
which is this part here, is the same
thing, this argument controls which
punctuation marks appear after
a word, that should be attached to the
previous words. It's the same thing,
but it's the inverse. Again, I could see
this, it's doable. So, if
you put this here, what it will do is paste
this punctuation you put
here in the word. So, for example, if
you have two tokens generating "ok", and then there's
a loose period, when you pass this
here, separately, the question mark will
sticking to the word at the end, resulting
in "ok?". And I left a tip
here, these punctuation arguments will
only make a noticeable difference if
you, for some reason, are using the
word's timestamp specifically
to see if the period is attached to a
word or not. For me, it didn't
make the slightest difference, because
I don't use these features, but
as I'm telling you, I tested each of
these options, one or another that I
couldn't test here. Alright, other
useful things, threads. Threads is the
number of threads you're going to use
from your computer. I tested with
1, 4, 10, 100, and 1000. What happened
was that basically my CPU was just
consuming more resources, but it didn't
change the transcription speed here.
This might make a difference on other
machines, it didn't on mine. But leave it
as default, default is 0, 0 it will use
as much as it needs and that's it. This
is interesting, --clip_timestamps, much
more used in my conception
for... uh, I just thought about the use
here, but let's say you want to get
a segment of the video, or several
segments, it can be all at once. You can
use this with seconds, with start and end.
So, for example, in this case, if
I say 10 and 30, what it will do is
transcribe only from the 10 seconds to the
30 seconds of that video. Nothing more
than that. But, besides that, you can also
pass this several times. So, I thought of
something like this useful for that
Here. First, for testing, I want to
test a specific section of the video, not
the whole thing, alright?
I might also want to transcribe, like
I was saying before, sections of
videos in different languages. This can
be interesting. Sometimes, from second
zero to 30, the person is speaking
French, then I transcribe all the parts
where they spoke French. Then I also
do another transcription, all the parts
where they spoke Portuguese, or any
other language. So, that was a use case
I thought of right now.
You can also pass several things.
So, it's always like this, beginning, end, start,
end. This works perfectly, but if you do
something like this, in this
In this case, when I passed it, it only starts the start,
right? So, it starts from this part and goes
all the way to the end. This might work, alright. For me, it worked
fine. It started at 4 minutes and 30 seconds and went to the end of the video. But
I tested it in a way that I don't think this was expected. It starting from
60, going up to 120, and then I just added a zero,
to see what it would do. It does
exactly what's written here. It starts
transcribing from 60, goes up to two, or
one minute to two minutes, ok, and
continues. But it continues as follows, it
goes back to the beginning of the video and translates to the
end. So, it seems that this wasn't
intended. If you see here, I even wrote.
Attention, this last case seems not to have
It was unexpected. Here it is, the zero
that comes after 120, there, makes the module
go back to the beginning of the transcription
and start over. This made my VLC player run
these subtitles, but it cut the initial
part of the video, for some reason. Even
though it went back to the beginning and
transcribed again, I think VLC reordered the
subtitles there, and what happened was that
it cut the initial part, even though it
did this here. It did this transcription,
but VLC cut it. So, this
is a case I wouldn't use, okay?
So, I would only use this like this, beginning,
end, beginning, end, maybe a beginning,
always after the previous one, but maybe
a beginning and not by end, it goes to the
end. This is also interesting.
In FFmpeg, you can do it with the -ss and -to flags.
You can use just one or the other as well.  If you only use -to, it
will only go up to that point, from the beginning to that point. If you only use -ss,
it will go from that -ss point to the end of the video. Okay.  And this other part here, I
haven't tested, didn't even touch this argument, but it's the `hallucination silence`
`threshold`. It works with `word timestamps` and tries to detect long periods of
silence where the model might have hallucinated, invented some text. If you
pass 1.5, it will ignore silences longer than 1.5 seconds, which generates suspicious text.
Again, I didn't touch this argument, you can test it yourself.
So, I'm reaching the end here of
the things. I think we went through
all the Whisper options here, okay? I
think you won't find any video
that deep about Whisper and at this
point we're only talking about the command
line of Whisper. We'll still have a
next video about Whisper talking
about code, that is, we're gonna do
something to embed
Whisper into our code and, you know,
do a transcription, something
like that. But, instead of doing that
in this video, which I think will take more
than an hour, we'll do that in the next
video together, alright? So that's it,
guys. See you in the next video.